So the public disclosure of dirtyc0w or CVE-2016-5195 just happened.
此漏洞由来已久，允许系统上的常规用户执行本地
privilege escalation and become root.
I want to show it to you, explore how it works and generally talk about it.
Let’s cut right to the chase and start by looking at the provided proof-of-concept exploit.
I have here a vulnerable Ubuntu system where I can downloa and compile the exploit.
Then I create a file owned by root to that I as a normal user can’t write to.
I can read it, but not write.
This is true for many files on the file system like for example the ping binary.
ping belongs to root and has the setuid bit set.
这意味着任何人都可以执行它，它将作为根目录运行，但是ping除了
sending out some networking traffic.
So our root file we just created resembles a file or binary like ping.
It’s owned by root and we can’t write to it.
现在，当我们执行dirtyc0w并将根文件传递给它并指定一个我们想要的字符串时
to write, we can observe, that the string got written to the file.
作为系统的常规用户，我们已经写入了一个根文件，但是我们没有
write access to.
This is insane.
现在假设我们已经在ping二进制文件中编写了一个后门，我们可以成为根
anytime.
Without knowing the password of root.
Now let’s try to understand the exploit code.
Let’s check out main() first where the code starts.
So first it opens the file we want to write to as READ_ONLY.
Next comes a call to mmap().
Mmap is used to create a new mapped memory segment in the current process.
其中一个参数可以是文件描述符，在本例中是只读文件
owned by root.
This means it maps the file into a new memory area.
Also the permission flags show, that this new memory area is READ_ONLY.
So far so good.
The other important flag is the MAP_PRIVATE flag.
这里的注释是从mmap的手册页复制的，它指出，这将创建一个
private copy-on-write mapping.
Or short C.O.W, cow.
This is where one part of the name for this vulnerability is from.
使用此标志，mmap不会将文件的全部内容复制到内存中，mmap映射
the file into your memory.
这太棒了，因为您不需要大量的RAM来加载文件副本，
you just directly read from the file on disk.
或者相对直接地，我们将在一秒钟内了解更多关于记忆的信息。
而copy-on-write意味着，如果你要写这个内存段，你会
then create a copy of it.
因此，尽管文件被映射为只读，但由于我们可以写入私有映射，因此
to a copy of it.
所以这里重要的是，mmap将根文件直接映射到
memory, and you can read the content of the file, or write to a COPY of it.
The changes to your copy should not be propagated to the real underlaying file.
这是给你的
Next we start two threads that will run in parallel.
dirtyc0w是一个种族条件漏洞，这意味着某些事件必须发生在
a specific order, that are fairly unlikely to happen under normal circumstances.
So you try to race against the probability of it not happenign.
And you simply try it over and over again.
And maybe you get lucky.
So let’s see what the two threads are doing.
The first thread is the madviseThread.
这个线程使用系统调用madvise，它可能不代表内存建议，
但是，疯狂的建议，我认为市场部在这里失败了，没有说出这种可能性。
疯牛，我说得对吗？
Ok. done with the dad jokes.
So this syscall can be used for optimization reasons.
您可以向内核提供一些关于如何使用内存映射区域的信息，
because there are different techniques how you handle caching, look ahead and so forth.
我们给内核的建议是，我们映射文件的内存区域
to, or at least the first 100 byte, is probably not needed anytime soon.
我们说，用马德夫·唐特纳的旗帜，它代表：
Do not expect access in the near future.
（目前，应用程序在给定范围内完成，因此内核可以释放
与之相关的资源。）
此范围内的后续页面访问将成功，但将导致重新加载
of the memory contents from the underlying mapped file.
The last sentence is key to the exploit.
Otherwise not much else happening here.
The other thread, procselfmemThread, opens the file /proc/self/mem.
This is a special file and I try to explain really quick.
So /proc is a so called pseudo filesystem.
In fact most resources on linux are managed as “files”.
So you should always see “files” in quotation marks when talking about them.
Imagine a file just to be something, you can read from, or write to.
所以这可能是打印机，写入打印机“文件”可能会导致
physical printer printing the string on a piece of paper.
So /proc does not really contain “files” in the common sense.
它们指的是更一般的东西，最重要的是对于我们的情况，你可以
read and write to.
So in this case /proc/self refers to special “files” provided for the current process.
So every process will have it’s own /proc/self.
其中有一个名为mem的“文件”，它表示当前进程的
memory.
So you could theoretically read your own process’s memory by reading from this file.
Now in this case, the exploit WRITES to this file in a loop.
因此，首先它执行一个查找，将当前光标移动到文件的开头，
we mapped into memory.
And then it writes the string we pass via the program arguments to it.
So this will trigger a copy of the memory, so that we can write to it and see these changes.
But remember, we will not write to the real underlaying file.
所以，如果你只做一次这些事情，或者只是孤立在一起，可能什么都没有。
would happen.
Because that would be the expected result.
但是因为在某个地方有一个种族条件的问题，反复尝试这个问题
将创建一个奇怪的边缘，通常不会发生，但在这种情况下，会欺骗
kernel into actually writing to the underlaying file.
现在让我们来看看这个补丁，因为我觉得这很有趣，而且不是很有趣
big.
所以在提交消息中，作者声明
这是一种古老的虫子，我十一年来一直试图修复一次。
在commit 4ceb5db9757a（“fix get_user_pages（）race for write access”）中，但那时
undone due to problems on s390 by commit f33ea7f404e5 ("fix get_user_pages bug").
所以我对我的IBM朋友有点失望，因为他们几乎有
partial guilt here.
S390 is the architecture used by IBM mainfraimes, system z.
Anyhow, let’s have a quick look.
The file that is patched belongs to the linux memory manager, hence the mm directory.
And the file itself is called GUP, which stands for get_user_pages.
Vm stands for virtual memory and pte for page table entry.
I think that should help a little bit to understand the code.
因此，当您想要写入这个映射内存时，内核必须复制它，因为
not allowed to write to the underlying file.
But a copy takes time.
现在通常你复印一次就可以了，但在这种情况下我们称之为疯子
DONTNEED over and over again.
Let’s look this up in the code.
So if this flag is used, this function is executed.
内核源代码解释了：
Application no longer needs these pages.
If the pages are dirty, it's OK to just throw them away.
The app will be more careful about data it wants to keep.
Be sure to free swap resources too.
I guess I quickly explain dirty.
This is also where the other part of the name is from.
When you read and write to disk you never do this directly, that would be wayyy to slow.
So you cache, or buffer them.
这意味着您将此数据保存在某个位置，并在某个时间点将其写入
disk.
Ok.
因此，如果您将数据从磁盘读取到内存中，您可以将其留在缓存中，
further reads.
但是，如果您想写入磁盘，您可以将它写入这个缓存/缓冲区，但是现在您可以
have to tell the system, that this buffer got touched and is dirty now.
It’s not clean fresh memory anymore.
在这种情况下，系统必须确保更改正确传播到底层。
physical memory.
Let it be a file on disk or flash memory.
因此，在本例中，如果您写入复制的mmaped内存，则会标记内存页。
dirty.
因为你现在告诉内核，页面不再需要了，这意味着
you don’t care that the dirty page has not been written yet.
You just toss it.
So this madvise call causes the throwing away of this memory.
This means it’s not in any of the memory caches anymore.
这对这种利用很重要，因为这意味着，每当我们试图写
to it again, the copy of the memory might have been tossed.
So we have to re load a new copy from memory so we can write to it.
And creating this copy takes time.
And this is the race condition, if the copy-on-write cycle is not complete yet.
补丁程序添加了这个函数来检查写入时的拷贝是否完成，以及
only then allows writing to it.
老实说，我真的不理解这段代码来告诉你为什么这段代码
sure that the copy on write is complete.
But it added some additional checks, so I assume now it’s fine.
So here is the mental picture of our race condition.
We constantly use madvise to drop any cached copy of the mapped file.
And at the same time we try to write to it, which causes a copy of that memory.
现在在一些罕见的情况下，只要反复尝试就可以非常可靠地击中它。
同样，我们在页表更新到点之前执行对内存的写操作。
us to our copied version.
And we write to the real file instead of the copied memory.
关于这个漏洞的疯狂之处在于，它已经在内核中存在了很长一段时间了。
long time.
根据补丁作者的说法，这甚至是一个已知的问题
to be patched before.
随着时间的推移，这个明显的理论竞赛条件变得可行，因为我们的系统
faster and faster.
And Petr Matousek also states, that this was an 0day exploit used in the wild.
So there was a real threat.
Now a bit of controversy.
这进入了腐朽者如何应对脆弱性的未解决的争论。
disclosure.
如果你是在野外发现这一漏洞的人，你会怎么做？
显而易见的论点是：
完全披露，因为它被积极利用，完全披露它马上就会
not given advanced attackers anything new.
但是这些知识将使系统管理员能够立即对
systems.
但另一方面，这是一个如此容易和普遍的弱点，一个充分披露
会让技术较差的黑客军队利用它，直到
professional sysadmins or private people could patch it.
另一方面，我们有一个负责任的披露，在这里您首先联系开发人员，创建
a fix, try to roll it out and then tell people afterwards.
这里的明显论点是，您停止了专业系统管理员对其进行热修补
system quickly and leave them exposed for the ongoing attacks.
Now I don’t know what is the best way.
Both ways have advantages and disadvantages.
And it entirely depends on your threat model.
一般来说，我更倾向于全面披露，因为我喜欢
be free, though I myself do responsible disclosure because I’m a hypocrite.
我希望你喜欢这种利用演练的视频，我可以给你看一些东西
new and interesting.
如果我说了错误的话，或者你有关于为什么必须触发此漏洞的其他信息
通过写入/proc/mem而不是直接写入地址，请更正我的错误。
或者在下面的评论中发布其他信息，以便其他关注的观众可以受益。
from it.
Thanks.